Guide to the Terhune and Wyckoff families papers ARC.279
Brooklyn Historical Society
Terhune and Wyckoff families papers
Bulk, 1800-1852
1747-1932
ARC.279
Brooklyn Historical Society
0.8 Linear feet in two manuscript boxes.
The Terhune and Wyckoff families papers (1747-1932) include documents of two prominent families, affiliated through marriage, from Gravesend in Kings County, New York (part of the New York City borough of Brooklyn after 1898). John Terhune (1767-1842) played a significant role in the early development of Coney Island as a resort location, and the collection includes some documents on that subject and on a dispute over whether to incorporate the town of Gravesend. The bulk of the collection, dating from the first half of the nineteenth century and likely compiled principally in connection with the administration of the estates of various Terhunes and Wyckoffs, includes bills, receipts, promissory notes, inventories, deeds, indentures, court filings, and other financial and legal documents. The collection holds several individual items of interest, including two letters commenting on the use of personal slanders as a tactic in political campaigns, a document related to the founding of the Agricultural Society of Kings County, six cartes-de-visite, bills of sale and a will referring to enslaved African-Americans, indentured servitude agreements, and a promissory note (1796) from Aaron Burr to Albert Terhune. Other names of Gravesend residents appearing frequently in the collection include Bennet, Emmans, Lake, Lott, Ryder, and Stillwell.
Terhune family
Wyckoff family
Conditions Governing Access note
Open to users without restriction.
Biographical/Historical note
Albert Terhune (1715-1806) was the great grandson of Albert Albertson Terhune, a Huguenot ribbon weaver from Holland who died in Flatlands, Long Island in 1685, having founded a family which spread through New Amsterdam, Long Island and Bergen County, New Jersey. The great grandson was a supervisor of the town of Gravesend, a member of the Gravesend Dutch Reformed Church (circa 1766) and an elder of that church (circa 1795). At his death in 1806, Albert left an apparently sizeable estate to his six surviving children: Abraham (1759-1840), Isaac (1762-1837), John (1767-1842), Anna (1750-circa 1826; m. Stryker), Margaret (1764-1840; m. John Wyckoff), and Maria (dates unknown; survived siblings and married twice: Emmons, Lott). A son, Roelef (b.1752) predeceased his father by a short time.
John Terhune was a judge in Gravesend and a supervisor of that town during the 1810s and 1820s. A founder of the Gravesend and Coney Island Road and Bridge Company, John fostered the development of Coney Island as a resort and recreation area for tired New Yorkers, to which end he and his brother Abraham backed the building of the first hotel there, the Coney Island House, in the 1820s. As an entrepreneur and financier, John does not appear to have always exercised the best judgment. In the 1810s and 1820s he was accused of having failed to account for public funds; he appears to have exonerated himself. At the time of his death in 1842, he had recently been served with notice of a sheriff's levy on his household goods for the benefit of creditors; he died insolvent and perhaps incompetent.
Shortly before his death in 1842, John wrote but failed to execute a will. The estate was beset with two major difficulties: the deceased's insolvency, which resulted in an estate sale of his furnishings and household goods, and, of greater significance, the fact of his intestacy, which resulted in a long litigation among relatives claiming rights to his real estate. His estate was administered by the sons of his sister Margaret, Albert Wyckoff and Jacob V. D. Wyckoff (1805-1857), a New York hardware merchant, and their brother-in-law, Abraham Van Siclen (m. Phebe Wyckoff, b. 179?).
Rights to the estate were litigated on the basis of Albert Terhune's will; the question was whether or not the terms could be construed to include the children of Albert's daughters as heirs, or whether the estate's distribution ended with Albert's children. The Wyckoff nephews and nieces were of the view that the first question should be answered in affirmative; the opposing view was taken by Marie Lott, Albert's last surviving child, and her husband. The affair was settled in 1852, apparently not greatly to the Wyckoff's favor. In 1878-1879, title to the lands once owned by John and Isaac Terhune was again questioned, and Albert T. Wyckoff, son of Jacob V. D. Wyckoff, was summoned to appear before the court.
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
The bulk of the collection was acquired in November 1956 from Paul Baylis of Middle Island, Long Island. Accession 1977.075 (the 1779 tax receipt) was a gift of Henry Onderdonk, Jr., date unknown. Accession 1974.158 (the 1814 Coney Island letter) was donated in January 1913 by Thomas D. Sugden of Bridgewater, CT (formerly of Flushing). Mr. Sugden also donated the materials in accession 1974.173, in 1903.
Related Archival Materials note
Brooklyn Historical Society holds other material related to this collection:
The William F. Wyckoff papers (call number 1978.002) includes a property map of Gravesend that relates to the Terhunes. There is also much material on the Wyckoffs, though not necessarily those Wyckoffs in this collection.
The Agricultural Society of Kings County (call number 1977.396) includes additional material on the organization that John Terhune co-founded.
Some Terhune material can also be found in the Lott family papers (call number ARC.186) and Bennet and Ryder families collection (call number ARC.001).
Material concerning the Terhunes and Wyckoffs can also be found in the BHS library by searching the on-line catalog, Bobcat, using the family names. Among the materials are maps and genealogies.
Scope and Contents
The Terhune and Wyckoff families papers span the years 1747-1932. They are primarily the records of family finances and estates administration for the period 1800-1858. These materials reflect the active lives of John Terhune and his brothers in Gravesend, Kings County, New York (now part of Brooklyn) and the difficult administration and litigation of John and Albert Terhune's estates.
The wealth of the collection for Brooklyn history lies in the documents concerning the Coney Island House, the Gravesend and Coney Island Road and Bridge Company, and Gravesend. There is a small but useful amount of correspondence concerning the effort to incorporate Gravesend, and the objections to it, each related to control over the letting of fishing rights. An 1814 letter provides an early recognition of the potential of Coney Island as a resort area. Although none of these institutions is by any means fully documented in the collection, they achieve a certain coherence in relation to the individual who was active in the direction of each. For this reason, John Terhune's business, legal and personal papers merit some attention as documentation of the public, official and financial affairs of a figure of stature in the town of Gravesend for a number of years. It is possible, too, that the legal records (accounts, opinions, complaints, deeds, etc.) generated both during the Terhunes' lifetime and during the administration of their estate will be of some value to those interested in local legal history, practice or procedure.
The bulk of the material in the collection is in the form of bills, receipts and promissory notes issued by or to the Terhune brothers, and notes or records kept by administrators of the estates of several Terhunes and Wyckoffs. Correspondence of any substance concerning estate administration is rare. With the exception of some printed legal forms (indentures, deeds, etc.) almost all of the papers are handwritten. In instances where items were unsigned, it was usually possible to identify the writer through his handwriting, if the writer was one whose records appear with frequency, as is the case with Jacob V.D. Wyckoff, Albert Wyckoff, and John Terhune to a lesser extent.
The collection also holds many individual items of interest, including two letters commenting on the use of personal slanders as a tactic in political campaigns, a document related to the founding of the Agricultural Society of Kings County, six cartes-de-visite, bills of sale and a will referring to enslaved African-Americans, indentured servitude agreements, and a promissory note (1796) from Aaron Burr to Albert Terhune. In addition to Terhune and Wyckoff, several other family names appear in the collection that are prominent in the history of the towns, especially Gravesend, that now comprise Brooklyn, New York. These names include Bennet, Emmans, Lake, Lott, Ryder, and Stillwell.
Arrangement note
Prior to being processed, the collection was in a state of nearly total disorganization. The lack of organization, the disparateness of the records, the number of individuals to whom they relate, and the lack of any substantial background information on the families or the collection itself made it difficult to perceive any pre-existent system of organization. There was considerable evidence, however, that the papers had been collected by Jacob V.D. Wyckoff and his son Albert T. Wyckoff. A great many of the items bear notations as to content in J.V.D.W.'s handwriting, indicating that he organized them in some fashion, probably in the course of estate administration.
An artificial scheme was therefore developed and imposed on the collection by the archivist in an effort to create a system of organization which might logically have been used by the executors and the persons whose affairs were in their hands. The dangers of an artificial system--possible errors in judgment, destruction of an existent system not readily apparent, or assumption of unverifiable relationships and functions--were weighed against the disadvantages of a more simple organization, such as by date or person. The former seemed better suited to bring to light the more valuable parts of the collection, while making the whole more easily accessible to researchers.
In its present state, therefore, the collection is arranged according to the function or activity of each individual, where applicable, or to a subject or institution. Records are arranged chronologically in each group; the overall arrangement of the collection is roughly chronological with respect to the Terhune estates. Documents of peripheral interest to the corpus are located in the latter part of the collection. Because of the disparateness of the records, the contents of most folders have been briefly highlighted in the container list below. Those few items found tied together during processing were kept together and are noted in the container list.
Coney Island House (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.).; Emmans family; Gravesend and Coney Island Bridge and Road Company.; Lott family; Stillwell family; Terhune family; Terhune, Albert; Terhune, John; Wyckoff family; African Americans |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Auctions |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Cartes-de-visite (card photographs); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Correspondence; Court records |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Deeds; Estate inventories.; Executors and administrators |z New York |z Kings County; Genealogies; Genealogy; Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Indentured servants |z New York (State) |z New York; Indentures; Inventories of decedents' estates |z New York (State) |z New York; Invoices; Kings County (N.Y.); Kings County (N.Y.) |x Genealogy; Legal documents |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Locomotive engineers; Promissory notes; Public officers |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Railroads |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Real property |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Receipts (financial records); Slave bills of sale; Tax records; Wills |z New York (State) |z Kings County
- Albert Terhune, 1766-1803 (Box 1, Folder 1a)
  General note
  Includes a promissory note to AT, with record of payments, from Aaron Burr and two receipts for purchases of slaves by AT.
- Albert Terhune: Tax Receipt, 1779 (Box 1, Folder 1b)
- Estate of Albert Terhune, 1803-1818 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Includes a certified copy of AT's will (which refers to a slave), receipts for payment of estate distribution, copy of a judge's opinion on the will. For post-1842 records, see f.1.14.
- Abraham Terhune, 1801-1839 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Includes documents concerning lawsuits; transfer of shares in Gravesend and Coney Island Road and Bridge Co.; Coney Island House payments; promissory notes; and text of advertisement for sale of land from Abraham's estate.
- John, Isaac and Abraham Terhune: Bills and Receipts, 1803-1835 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Includes financial transactions involving various Terhunes, such as bonds, invoices and receipts for grocery purchases, a slave, medical attention, and the like.
- John Terhune: Correspondence, 1800-1842 (Box 1, Folder 5a)
  Includes an 1800 letter in which the writer conveys to JT, then proposed for state Assembly, public speculation that he harbors undemocratic principles; a minister's unwillingness to preside at a burial of another minister's congregant; requests from JT's nephew, J. Emmans, for money due him from an estate; and notice of Sheriff's sale of house and JT's inquiry thereon.
- John Terhune: Correspondence: Coney Island Proposal, 1814 (Box 1, Folder 5b)
- John Terhune: Bills, 1803-1842 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Includes financial documents, such as bills for clothing, household items, services, farm expenses; promissory notes and interest payments; and notes to Abraham, some of which were bound together, apparently by an executor, with the note "These notes were said to constitute that claim, upon which the Executors of Abraham Terhune got the Coney Island House."
- John Terhune: Business, circa 1797-1833 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Includes a resolution for the formation of a society for the "promotion of agriculture and rural economy"; certificate of JT's appointment as Quarter Master of the 1st regiment of the 1st brigade of the N.Y. cavalry; indenture witnessed by JT; indenture of a boy apprentice to JT; and financial documents. Related to f.1.8 and f.1.10.
- John Terhune: Legal Papers, 1808-1836 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes items concerning the Kings County Court of Common Pleas, reflecting JT's activity as judge; many appear to be in his handwriting. Includes an incomplete draft of petition to the U.S. Congress, objecting to the military's seizure of farm lands at the Narrows of New Utrecht; several executed and unexecuted deeds and other agreements; a court filing by a defendant, James Hatch, in a case concerning damages of goods held onboard a ship; account of court fees; and record of JT's appointment as arbitrator in a local dispute. Related to f.1.7 and f.1.10.
- Terhune Family: Miscellaneous Documents, 1768-1830 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Includes an advertisement by Albert Terhune concerrning stolen corn; fire insurance policy to Abraham and John Terhune on a house in Gravesend; notes of charges against Elias Hubbard, an elder of the Flatlands Dutch Church, including a complaint by A. Terhune; a draft will of Samuel Hubbard; and the will of Isaac Emmans (Terhunes, executors).
- Gravesend, 1816-1825 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Includes JT correspondence with a Roger Strong in Albany on the incorporation of Gravesend, including concerns over fishing rights; list of objectors to the incorporation; drafts of petitions; and notices of accusations against JT for failure to account for funds as Supervisor of Gravesend.
- Gravesend and Coney Island Road and Bridge Co., 1824-1841 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Includes proxies, power of attorney to JT; records on dividends; bills for advertising election; memo addressed to state legislature for right to recapitalize. See also f.1.3.
- Coney Island House, 1823-1837 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Includes bills and receipts of John and Abraham Terhune for construction; correspondence concerning rent; description of proposed house; correspondence concerning an artillery company's stay at the House. Related to f.1.3, f.1.6, f.1.11.
- Estate of John Terhune, 1842-1852 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Includes JT's unexecuted will; forms from Surrogate of Brooklyn for sale of personal property by executors; inventories and lists of sales; letter to Anna Terhune (Isaac's widow) from JT's heirs, requesting permission to remove JT's body from her property.
- Estate of Albert Terhune: post-1842, 1842-1852 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Includes legal opinions, decisions, papers relating to devisees of will. See also f.1.3.
- Terhune Estates, 1841-1853 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  Items found tied together prior to processing and including an opinion on the will of Albert Terhune, notes on executors' accounts, etc. All on same size, color and quality paper and were probably copies made by or for J.V.D. Wyckoff.
- Terhune Estates Legal Papers, 1842-45, 1878-1879 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  Includes accounts of court expenses incurred in litigation; power of attorney; service of notice to appear before court. A Kings County Supreme Court summons lays out the complex estate controversy.
- Terhune Estates: Miscellaneous, 1823-1853 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  Includes items relating variously to estates of Isaac, Roelef, Anna Terhune Stryker, and Margaret Terhune Wyckoff. Receipts and executors' notes. Includes a document by J.V.D. Wyckoff on family members and marriages.
- Terhune Estates: Executors' notes, 1842-1844 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  Includes two partially filled notebooks, a check and miscellaneous jottings. Most appear to be product of J.V.D. Wyckoff. Related to f.2.1, f.2.9.
- Estate of J. Van Nuys, 1827-1843 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  Items dealing with estate of Jane Van Nuys, administered by John Terhune.
- Abraham Van Siclen, 1811, 1832 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  Includes a deed from Isaac Emmans (1811), bills and receipts.
- Albert Wyckoff, 1825-1850 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  Includes bills and farm records for Terhune Farm, 1844-45. See also f.2.9 for correspondence between Albert and J.V.D. Wyckoff on estates.
- Bennet, 1832-1850 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  Items found tied together before processing, with exception of one notebook on administrative accounts added to file. Principally bills, receipts, accounts. Catherine Wyckoff Bennet (1797-1850), daughter of Margaret Terhune and John Wyckoff. Papers pertain to her share in her father's estate, administered by Abraham Van Siclen and Albert Wyckoff.
- Jacob V.D. Wyckoff, 1842-1858 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  Includes correspondence with Albert Wyckoff and notes on Terhune Estates. 1858 document relates to Jacob V.D.Wyckoff's own estate. Related to f.2.l, f.2.4.
- George Wyckoff, 1842-1844 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  Includes bills and receipts under account administered by Jacob V.D.W. during George W.'s lifetime, and a bill of sale for house under George's estate.
- Roelef T. Wyckoff, 1840-1846 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  Includes items dealing principally with financial matters.
- Dutch Church of Flatlands, 1747 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  Includes an unexecuted deed from Wilhemus Stoothoff to the Church.
- Sales and Auctions, 1825-1847 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Includes lists of household furnishings auctioned and of purchasers, similar to those in f.1.13.
- Bills and Receipts: Miscellaneous, 1799-1840 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- Albert T. Wyckoff, 1849-1881 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Includes school commendation certificates (i.e., school premiums) from New York Ward Schools 14 and 29 and from the Mechanics' Institute; Wyckoff genealogical notes and correspondence collected in response to a request by Teunis Bergen; a bill of sale for the schooner Rebecca and Harriet; and correspondence from L. Bradford Prince, state senatorial candidate from Flushing (1875), asking for support and objecting to his opposition's tactics of personal slander.
- Albert T. Wyckoff: Bills, 1874-1888 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Includes hotel bills (Canada), bills or receipts for coal, newspapers, Brooklyn taxes, bond and mortgage, etc.
- Henry Wyckoff: Long Island Railroad, 1929-1932 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Includes engineer's notes, such as hours and pay, arrival at stations, mechanical issues, etc. Many notes written on back of notices sent by Railroad offices.
- Ephemera, 1859-1887 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Includes an issue of Contra Costa Gazette, Martinez, California newspaper (Aug. 6,1859); Samuel A. Goddard and Co. (Birmingham, UK) List of prices of hardware, guns, saddlery,.. ., with prices handwritten in (1850s?); a bill for coal (1883); and clipping of a poem "If I should die tonight" (1887).
- Cartes-de-visite, circa 1864 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Includes 6 images: George P. Barrett of the 7th regiment, N.Y.S. National Guard; J. B. Preswick of the 7th Minnesota Volunteers; Eldon P. Lighthill; George Meyers; Dr. C. B. Lighthill; one unidentified man.